So as our first example lets look at a
very simple way of using a block cipher
那么作为我们的第一个例子，让我们看一个十分简单的使用分组密码
for encryption. In particular we'll see
how to use a block cipher with a one time
的加密。特别的，我们看看怎么使用具有一次性密钥的分组密码
key. So in this segment we're just gonna
use the block cipher to encrypt using keys
所以在这一节我们将使用一次性密钥的分组密码来加密
that are used one time. In other words,
all the adversary gets to see is one ciphertext,
换句话说，攻击者看到的将仅仅是一份密文
and its goal is to break semantic
security of that ciphertext. Now, in the
他的目标将是破解密文的语义。现在，
next segment, we're going to turn into
more, interesting applications of block
在下一段中，我们将了解更有意思的分组密码的应用
ciphers and we're going to see how to
encrypt using keys that are used many,
以及如何使用密钥对多组信息进行多次加密
many times to encrypt many messages. So
before we start, I want to mention that
那么在我们开始之前，我想要提的一点是
there's like a classic mistake in using a
block cipher. Unfortunately, there are some
一个使用分组密码的经典错误。不幸的是，有许多产品
products that actually work this way, and
they are badly broken, so I want to make
正是这么工作的，它们被完全的破解了，所以我想要确信
sure that none of you guys actually make
this mistake. So this mode of operation is
你们中没人会犯这个错误。这种操作模式
called an electronic code book. And it
works as follows: it's the first thing
被称为电子密码本。它如下工作：
that comes to mind when you want to use a
block cipher for encryption. What we do is
它将是你想用分组密码来加密时首先想到的。我们
we take our message, we break it into
blocks, each block as big as the block's
拿到我们的信息并将之分块，每一块都和加密块一样大小
cipher block. So in the case of AES, we
would be breaking our message into sixteen
那么在AES的例子中，我们将把我们的信息分成16字节的块
byte blocks. And then we encrypt each
block separately. So this mode is often
然后分别加密我们的每一块。这种模式常被称为
called electronic codebook. And,
unfortunately, it's terribly insecure
电子代码本。不幸的是这是很不安全的
because you realize if two blocks are
equal, for example here, these two blocks
因为你意识到如果两块是相同的，比如
happen to be equal, then necessarily the
resulting ciphertext is also going to be equal.
有两个块恰好是相同的，那么必然导致密文也是相同的
So an attacker who looks at the
ciphertext, even though he might not know
那么一个分析密文的攻击者，即使他可能不知道
what's actually written in these blocks,
we'll know that these two blocks are
这些块到底写了什么，但会知道这些块是相同的
equal. And as a result, he learned
something about the plaintext that he
那么，结果就是他知道了关于明文的一些他不该知道的信息
shouldn't have learned. And if this isn't
clear enough for you abstractly, the best
如果这么讲不够清楚，最好的解释是
to explain this is using a picture. And so
here's this guy here that, you know, has
用一副图。这有一个家伙，你知道他有
this really dark black hair. And when we
encrypt. This image, this bitmap image
深黑色的头发。那么我们用电子密码本模式
using the electronic code book mode. You
see that his hair, that contains lots of
加密这幅位图。你看他占大量空间的头发
ones. Basically always gets encrypted the
same way, so that his silhouette,
基本上总是被用相同的方式加密，这是他的剪影
actually, is completely visible, even in
the encrypted data. Okay, so this is a
事实上，这是完全可见的，即使是在加密的数据中。所以
nice example of how the electronic code
book mode can actually leak information
这是一个电子密码本可能泄露给攻击者关于
about the plaintext that could tell
something to the attacker. So the question
明文的信息的例子。那么问题是
is, how to correctly use block ciphers to
encrypt long messages. And so, I just
如何正确的用分组密码来加密长的信息。那么，我将
want to briefly remind you of the notion
we're trying to achieve, which is
简单的提醒你我们将要实现的想法，就是简单
basically semantic security using a one
time key. So the adversary outputs two
的用一次性密钥保证语义安全。那么攻击者
messages, m0 and m1, and then he gets
either the encryption of m0 or the
输出两组信息，M0和M1，那么当他将得到M1或M2的加密。
encryption of m1, these are two different
experiments. And then our goal is to say
有两组不同实验，我们的目标是确定
that the adversary can't distinguish
between these two experiments. So you
攻击者不能将两者区分开来，
can't distinguish the encryption of m0
from the encryption of m1. And the reason
也就是说，你不能区分M0的加密和M1的加密。
we call this security for a one time key
is that the key is only used to encrypt a
我们认为一次性密钥是安全的原因是这个密钥只被用来加密
single message. And as a result, the
adversary will ever only see one ciphertext
一组信息。于是，攻击者可能只会见到一份
encrypted using this key. Okay, so
the first thing we want to show is that in
用了这组密钥的密文。好了，我们想要展示的第一件事是
fact the mode we just looked at,
electronic code book, in fact, is not
事实上我们刚看的模式，电子密码本，事实上不是语义安全的。
semantically secure. And this is true as
long as you're encrypting more than one
只要你加密不止一个块他就不是语义安全的
block. So here's an example. Suppose we
encrypt two blocks using a block cipher.
这有一个例子。假设我们用分组密钥加密两块
Let me show you that in fact electronic
code book will not be secure. So here's
我来向你们证明电子密码本实际上是不安全的
what we would do. So we're the adversary.
So we would output two messages, m0 and
我们将这么做。假设我们是攻击者。我们输出两个信息，m0和m1
m1, where, in one message, the blocks are
distinct, and in the other message, the
在一个信息中，分组是不同的，另一个中，分组是相同的。
blocks are the same. The two blocks are
equal to one another. Well, so what is the
这两个分组相同，那么挑战者要如何做？
challenger gonna do? The challenger's
going to encrypt either m0 or m1.
挑战者将要加密m0或m1
Either way we are gonna get two blocks
back. So the ciphertext actually contains two
两种情况我么都得到两个分组，那么密文包含两个分组
blocks. The first block is going to be an
encryption of the word "Hello" and the
第一个分组是单词“Hello”的加密
second block is gonna be either an
encryption of the word "Hello" or the word
第二个分组是“Hello”或“World”的加密
"World". And if the two ciphertext blocks
are the same then the adversary knows that
如果这两个密文分组一样，那么攻击者知道
he received an encryption of the message
"Hello Hello" and as a difference he knows
他收到是“Hello Hello”的加密
that he received encryption of the
message "Hello World". Okay? So, he just
如果不一样，他知道他收到是“Hello World”的加密。对吧
follows a simple strategy here. And if you
think about it for a second, you'll see
所以，攻击者遵循一个简单的策略，大家想一想，就可以知道他的优势是什么
what his advantage is. So, what is the
advantage? Well, this adversary when he
那么优势是什么呢？
received an encryption of the message
m1 he will always output 0.
攻击者总在他接收到m1的加密时输出0
and when he receives an encryption of
the message m0 it will always output 1.
总是在他接收到m0的加密时输出1
And because of that the advantage,
basically, is 1, which means that the
由于优势是1，也就是说这种机制是不安全的
scheme is not secure, which again shows you
the electronic code book is not
也再次表明，电子密码本不是语义安全的
semantically secure and should never ever
be used to encrypt messages that are more
永远不应被用来加密长于一个分组的信息
than one block long. So, what should we
do? Well, so here's a simple example. What
那么我们该怎么办？有个简单的例子
we could do is we could use what's called
a deterministic counter mode. So in a
我们可以使用一个确定的计数器模式
deterministic counter mode, basically we
build a stream cipher out of the block
在确定的计数器模式下，我们主要用分组密码构建一个流密码
cipher. So suppose we have a PRF, F. So
again you should think of AES when I say
假设我们有一个伪随机函数(PRF) f。我说PRF时大家应该可以想到AES,
that. So AES is also a secure PRF. And
what we'll do is, basically, we'll evaluate
AES也是一个安全的PRF。我们要做的基本上就是
AES at the point zero, at the point one,
at the point two, up to the point L. This
计算AES在点0处的值，在点1处的值，在点2处的值，一直到点L
will generate a pseudo random pad. And I
will XOR that with all the message
这会产生一个伪随机密码本，我会将他和所有明文分组进行异或
blocks and recover the ciphertext as a
result. Okay, so really this is just a
得到密文作为结果
stream cipher that's built out of a PRF,
like AES and triple DES, and it's a simple
这其实只是一个由PRF构造的流密码。同AES和3DES一样，是个简单的加密方法
way to do encryption. I wanted to just
very quickly show you the security
我想很快的为大家证明这个安全定理
theorem. In fact, we've already seen the
security theorem when it applied to stream
事实上，我们已经讨论使用PRF的流密码时已经看到过这个安全定理了。
ciphers using pseudo-random generators, so
I'm not going to repeat this again. I'll
所以我不打算将他重复一遍
just remind you that essentially for every
adversary A that's trying to attack
我只是提醒大家，对每个试图攻击确定计数器模式的攻击者A
deterministic counter mode, we prove that
there's an adversary B that's trying to
我们证明存在一个试图攻击PRF的攻击者B
attack the PRF. And since this quantity is
negligible, because the PRF is secure, we
由于这个量是可以忽略的，因为PRF是安全的
obtain that this quantity is negligible.
And therefore, the adversary has
我们得到这个量也是可忽略的。因此，
negligible advantage in defeating
deterministic counter mode. And the
这个攻击者对确定的计数器模式只有一个可忽略的优势
proof in pictures is a really simple
proof. So I'll just show it to you one
这个证明用图形表示很简单，为求完整，
more time for completeness. So basically,
what we want to show is, when the
我就为大家再证明一次
adversary's given the encryption of the
message m0, here, this is the encryption
当攻击者有明文m0的加密时，这是m0的加密密文
of the message, m0. m0 XOR counter
applied to the PRF, versus in giving the
m0异或计数器的PRF值
encryption of the message, m1. We wanna
argue these two distributions are
或是m1的加密。我们想证明这两个分布
computationally indistinguishable. So the
way we do that is basically we say, well
是计算上不可区分的。那么基本证明方法是
the top distribution, if instead of a PRF,
we use a truly random function, namely
上面这个分布，如果我们用真随机函数，不是PRF。比如，
here f is a truly random function, then
the adversary, because of the property of
这里f是一个真随机函数，那么由于PRF的性质
the PRF, the adversary cannot distinguish
these two experiments, right. A PRF is
攻击者不能区分两个实验。
indistinguishable from a truly random
function, therefore when we replace the PRF
一个PRF和一个真随机函数是无法区分的，
on the left with a truly random function
on the right, the adversary is going to
所以当我们用右边的真随机函数替换左边的PRF时
behave the same. Basically you can't
distinguish these two distributions. But
攻击者的行为是不会变的，你无法区分这两个分布
now because F is a truly random function,
the pad here is a truly one time pad, and
但现在因为f是一个真随机函数，这个密码本是真的一次性密码本
therefore no adversary can distinguish an
encryption of m0 from an encryption of m1
因此没有攻击者能够区分在一次性密码本下的
under the one time pad. So, again, these
two distributions are the same. In fact,
m0和m1的加密。因此这两个分布是一样的
here there's an actual equality. These two
distributions literally are the same
事实上，这有一个等式。这两个分布
distribution. And similarly again when we
go back from a truly random function here
就是一样的分布。类似的，当我们从一个真随机函数
to a PRF, because the PRF is secure, the
adversary can't distinguish these two
回到一个PRF时，因为PRF是安全的，所以攻击者无法区分
bottom distributions, the left from the
right. And so by following these three
下面这两个分布，左边的和右边的。
equalities, basically we have proven that
the things we wanted to prove equal are
根据下面这三个等式，我们证明了这些我们希望证明相等的东西
actually computationally
indistinguishable. Okay, so that's a very
实际上计算不可区分的
simply proof to show that deterministic
counter mode is in fact secure and it's
这是一个非常简单的证明来表明确定的计数器模式，事实上是安全的
basically the same proof as we had when we
proved that a stream cipher gives us
这个证明和我们之前证明流密码的语义安全是一样的
semantic security. Okay. So that completes
this segment and in the next segment we'll
好，本节完成。下节我们将讨论
talk about modes that enable us to use a
key to encrypt multiple messages.
能够让我们使用一个密钥加密多个信息的加密模式